What's going on engineers. The
question today is what is Linux
used for. Let's talk about that,
let's also talk about where you
might use it and then also some
common and uncommon places that
you might find Linux, and this
is one of your first Linux
videos you're not even sure what
it is you could pick up Linux as
similar to Windows or Mac OS,
with a few key differences, and
the big differences are that
Linux is a free and open
platform and this free as in
cost, but also in freedom, it's
also a lot smaller, and it's
also very flexible. And it's
that flexibility is why it's
used for so many things. In
fact, there's a lot of people
that use Linux every day without
even realizing it, and we'll
talk about that in a second. So
let's get started. Before we get
started I have several things
and I've ordered them roughly in
terms of how dominant Linux is
in a given area, which brings us
to the first thing Linux is used
for and that's super computing,
and this area is an area where
Linux is the undisputed grand
champion in terms of market
share in 2020, at least 99% of
all supercomputers are running
Linux. The purpose number one
spot was held by Unix and really
there was no other platform that
ever even came close to either
Unix or Linux, nowadays came out
in 1991 but it took about eight
years for it to mature before it
started being used in
supercomputing. But once I got a
foothold in that was there for
UNIX, from 2000 to 2010 It went
from 5% market share to 90%
market share. That's a pure
reason why Linux is adoption
supercomputing was both broad
and rapid but it comes down to
one thing and that was the
openness of the platform, being
able to create a customized
distribution just for
supercomputing is hugely
beneficial, and that's just
something that Unix can't do the
next year it seems says mobile
devices, the largest most widely
deployed mobile platform on
planet earth, of course is
Android. In terms of market
share, it's probably a lot
higher in 86% chose that number
because that's just to Android
only if you take other mobile
device platforms such as
postmarket OH S which is pure
Linux as opposed to Android
which is based on Linux and that
number probably goes north of
90%. So if you own an Android
phone then you benefit from
Linux, every single day. The
next thing Linux is used for and
this is a huge one is cloud
computing. In fact, this very
video that you're watching right
now is 100% for sure served to
you by a Linux server somewhere
in the cloud. It's hard to say
exactly what the market share is
here is thought to be about 84%
for Linux and just to Google,
Facebook, IBM, and Amazon alone
have around 4 million servers, I
have to imagine there's 10s of
millions of servers worldwide
maybe even 100 million and the
vast majority of those are going
to be running Linux. But to be
sure this is an area where Linux
is not completely dominant,
there are huge data centers out
there running Windows Server
software, and there's several
sites that run on Microsoft
technologies. One of the main
ones is Stack Exchange, although
I think they only have about 100
servers. Another major area
where Linux is found is IoT
devices, and that's whether it's
your ring doorbell on the front
of your house, your google home
your Amazon Alexa or the Nest
thermostat on your wall, every
single one of those things are
running Linux, roughly 75% of
all IoT devices are running
Linux, then the remainder are
probably just bare metal
operating systems or something
proprietary Linux is a real
logical choice for IoT stuff
because it's small and it
already has a lot of the tech
stacks available to do common
things that you would do in an
IoT device such as maybe
Bluetooth or Wi Fi or
interfacing with hardware or
otherwise, for a manufacturing
standpoint, who's designing a
new IoT product and they want to
offer it both quick and cheap,
it makes sense to just pick
Linux which already does a lot
of the core stuff they're going
to need. The next place to find
Linux to use is as a replacement
for something like Windows or
Mac OS, you can use Linux on the
desktop. In fact, right now I'm
recording this video on Linux,
and when I'm done recording I'm
going to edit it on Linux.
Unfortunately the Linux desktop
market share is embarrassingly
low and that's due to the fact
that it is kind of user
unfriendly although that
improves as each year goes by,
as a Linux enthusiast myself I
always hold out hope that this
year will be the year polemics
desktop. The next place we'll
find Linux is in self driving
cars. And this is true of both
Tesla's as well as the Google
self driving car in the best
drug cases outside of Google and
Tesla if a car manufacturer is
making a self driving platform,
then they're going to be using
Linux as its base. Did you know
you can find Linux on things
like washing machines and
coffeemakers. Well, now you do
that late model Samsung washing
machine that you have that lets
you check on your phone to see
the stands that are closing
around the world, you can bet
that it's running Linux. And
finally, and this one is really
cool with the Large Hadron
Collider runs on Linux across
it's hundreds of 1000s of cores
and it's 10s if not hundreds of
petabytes of collision data,
Linux, indeed did contribute to
the discovery of the Higgs Boson
particle. For those curious I
believe they use the CERN
developed scientific Linux. So
the summary here is that Linux
is prolific and it's used in so
many different places for so
many different things, and as
the years go by the number of
things continue to increase. If
you have any questions about
anything you saw in this video
or if you want to share other
places that you know Linux exist
or how you use Linux I did it
basis you should let me know in
the comments below. Alright that
next video take care.